Guide to the Dana Paul Mitchel Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Dana Paul Mitchel Papers,
[ca. 1925]-1960
Mitchell, Dana Paul, 1899-1966.
ca. 1,500 items (4 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079115
History
Professor of physics at Columbia University, 1921-1966. Columbia University, Ph.D., 1936.
Scope and Content
Professional and personal correspondence, administrative records, manuscript lecture notes, and some miscellaneous printed materials. The general correspondence file, 1927-1958, contains letters, both personal and professional, with colleagues, with and about his students, about laboratory equipment, about weapons for the Army and Navy, and with industry concerning his research. The subject file, 1926-1960, contains some additional professional and personal correspondence, a number of administrative records on property control of laboratory equipment, particularly for government research projects, other Columbia Physics Department matters, several typescripts on cyclotron coil designs, Mitchell's personal records relating to employment, and other miscellaneous personal files. There are handwritten lecture notes for Mitchell's courses, the most complete being those for Physics R6 and General Studies Physics 18.
Subjects
Columbia University.--Physics Dept.; United States.--Army.; United States.--Navy.; Cyclotrons--Designs and plans.; Industries.; Physics--Research.; Physics--Laboratories.; Physics--Study and teaching.; Physicists.; College teachers.
Access Restrictions
3 boxes of arranged material are shelved off-site and require advance notice of intent to use.
Acquisition
1978 M-78 Physics Department Transfer
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Fermi, Enrico (Box 1)
  - Pegram, George B. (Box 1)
- Series II: Correspondence Files, 1927-1958
  - 1927-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1958 (Box 1)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1926-1960
  - Apparatus (Box 1)
  - Appointments (Box 1)
  - Berkeley Radiation Laboratory (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketches of Mitchell (Box 1)
  - Boats (Box 1)
  - Co1mnbia College Faculty (Box 1)
  - Columbia University -Personnel File for Mitchell (Box 1)
  - Color Code Marking (Box 1)
- Series IV: Subject Files, 1926-1960
  - Committee on Undergraduate Instruction (Box 2)
  - Cyclotron Coils -Miscellaneous Design Papers (Box 2)
  - Davis, Bergen -Books (Box 2)
  - Faculty of Pure Science -Misc. Memos (Box 2)
  - Los Alamos Project (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, Dana P. -Misc. Personal Materials (with a snapshot) (Box 2)
  - Physics R6 (Box 2)
  - Physics Department Misc. Memos (Box 2)
  - Property Control:
    - -Carbide and Chemicals Corp. Fellowships (Box 2)
    - -Columbia Radiation Laboratory (Box 2)
    - -Decals (Box 2)
    - -"N.B." (Box 2)
    - -Nevis Laboratories (Box 2)
    - -"Project Michael" (Box 2)
    - -Rabi's Navy Contract (Box 2)
    - -Government Surplus (Box 2)
  - Sales Catalogs -Sales Catalogs for equipment (Box 2)
  - Systems for Purchase, Distribution & Inventory Control of Property, 29 Sep. 1943 (Box 2)
- Series V: Lecture Notes
  - Physics R6 (Box 3)
  - General Studies Physics 18 (Box 3)
- Series VI: Lecture Notes
  - Physics R7 (Box 4)
  - Physics S3 (Box 4)
  - Hoops and Rolling Problems; Waves; Gavitation (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials (Box 4)